Guide to the Richard L. Maury papers, 1824-1940 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard L. Maury papers 1824-1940 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Maury, Richard L. (Richard Lancelot), 1840-1907.
10.8 linear feet Extent: Approx. 5731 Items
Confederate soldier and lawyer, of Richmond, Virginia. Collection comprises correspondence, diaries, journals, booklets, maps, bills and receipts, legal papers, genealogical material, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, and other records relating to Richard Maury's business and personal affairs, and the history of the Maury family. Includes material on his Civil War experiences, including a Civil War scrapbook, his attempt to establish a settlement of southerners in Mexico after the Civil War, life in Mexico and Nicaragua, Confederate veterans' views on prominent battles of the Civil War, and student life at the University of Virginia in the 1880s. Correspondents include his father, Matthew Fontaine Maury (1806-1873) and members of the Maury family.
RL.00886
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Richard L. Maury Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1964.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises the papers of Richard Launcelot Maury (1840-1907), his wife, Susan Gatewood (Crutchfield) Maury, and his son, Matthew Fontaine Maury III (b. 1863), and papers relating to many other members of the Maury family, including Richard L. Maury's father, Matthew Fontaine Maury (1806-1873). Correspondence contains letters written in 1824 by Dabney M. Herndon and his family, especially his daughter, Ann Hull Herndon, who became the wife of Matthew F. Maury (1806-1873); correspondence, 1856, 1858, 1860, of Matthew F. Maury concerning his investments in land in Minnesota; a few letters and papers of Richard L. Maury, Matthew F. Maury, and John H. Maury from the period of the Civil War, mainly concerning Richard's service with the 24th Virginia Regiment and John's experiences in Mississippi; copies of letters, 1865, of Matthew F. Maury concerning the post of "Imperial Commissioner of Colonization" which he accepted from Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico; and letters from 1865 to 1868 describing life in Mexico and Nicaragua.
Later correspondence includes letters, 1881 to 1885, from Matthew F. Maury III (b. 1863), as a student at the University of Virginia and at the Columbian University Law Department in Washington, D.C.; letters, 1886, of Matthew F. Maury III, while on a European tour, correspondence of the law firm of Richard L. Maury and Matthew F. Maury III; correspondence of Richard L. Maury with Civil War veterans concerning battles in which he fought, and letters pertaining to Confederate veterans' organizations; and letters relating to Huguenot ancestors.
Legal papers contain land deeds of various members of the Maury family; Mexican land grants and legal papers; papers related to legal cases involving the Universal Life Insurance Company of New York and Euqenia M. Horde v. Wheeling Lands; survey reports and maps; and the wills of Matthew F. Maury and Richard L. Maury. Financial papers include records of Maury and Letcher, 1869-1874; papers concerning the financial affairs of C. W. Maury and Company, New York stockbrokers Richard L. Maury, 1873-1907; and financial records of Matthew F. Maury.
Collection also contains genealogical material on the Maury family and several related families, and a history of the Maury family by Richard L. Maury; a number of Confederate bonds; school reports of Matthew F. Maury III; clippings, published speeches, and pamphlets, for the most part dealing with the Civil War, including Richard L. Maury's In Memoriam, a tribute to Matthew F. Maury; journal from 1886 of the European tour of Matthew F. Maury III; a notebook of Matthew F. Maury III on the sermons of Dr. Charles Minnigerode of St. Paul's Church, Richmond, Virginia; the journal of Richard L. Maury kept while on a trip to London, England, 1873; expense account for European trips taken by Richard L. Maury's family, 1890, 1892; Richard L. Maury's expense accounts, 1869-1907; diary of Richard L. Maury, 1866-1867; diary of Ann Maury, 1889; and a scrapbook of clippings, 1861-1865, mainly from the Richmond Enquirer and the Richmond Whig, concerning the Civil War.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Maury, Richard L. (Richard Lancelot), 1840-1907; Maury family; Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1806-1873; Confederate States of America. Army -- Officers; University of Virginia -- Students; Lawyers -- Virginia -- Richmond; Universities and colleges -- Virginia; Southern States -- Emigration and immigration; Mexico -- Description and travel; Nicaragua -- Description and travel; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Veterans; Diaries; Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- Richard L. Maury Papers, 1824-1940 and undated, (27 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1824-1869 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1877 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1878-1881 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1882-1884 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1885-1890 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1891-1896 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1897 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1900 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1906 (1902-1906 folder relates to Mary Werth, et al.) (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1907-1940 and undated (Box 10)
  - Letters and other materials relating to Marye vs. Parsons, 1850-1899 (Box 11)
  - Addresses and articles, notes and maps on the Battles of Seven Pines and Drewry's Bluff (Box 12)
  - Letters and legal papers related to the South Salem Land Company, 1894-1899 (Box 13)
  - Legal papers, 1854-1908 and undated (Box 14)
  - Legal papers: Hodge vs. Wheeling Lands; Universal Life Insurance Company (Box 15)
  - Bills, receipts, etc., 1859-1899 (Box 16)
  - Miscellany, pictures, genealogy (Box 17)
  - Bills and receipts, 1900-1909 and undated (Box 18)
  - Bills and receipts (Thomas Branch and Co., 1890-1905) (Box 19)
  - Bills and receipts (Thomas Branch and Co., 1890-1905) (Box 20)
  - Bills and receipts (Thomas Branch and Co., 1890-1905), canceled checks, volumes (Box 21)
  - Volumes (Box 22)
  - Volumes - sermons, etc (Box 23)
  - Volumes (Box 24)
  - Volumes - Civil War scrapbook (Box 25)
  - Printed material and clippings (Box 26)
  - Bills and receipts, Letcher and Maury papers, financial papers, C.W. Maury and Co. papers, 1869-1907 (Box 27)